Finding Aid for Fraternity Office (University of Michigan)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fraternity Office (University of Michigan)records 1922-1965, 1958-1964
University of Michigan. Fraternity Office.
0.5 linear feet
87175 Bimu F45 2
Records, 1922-1965, of the Fraternity Office of the University of Michigan. Documents activities of the Interfraternity Council and the Interfraternity Alumni Assembly. Also contains folders for individual fraternities and sororities and includes histories, member lists, and information about disciplinary action taken against fraternities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The source of the transfer of this record group is unknown. NO.
The record group is open without restriction.
The history of the Fraternity Office dates back to the 1938/39 academic school year when the experimental position "Fraternity Relations Counselor" was created by Dean Joseph Bursley (Dean of Men). This experimental position was created to define and clarify the relationship between the university and fraternities and to coordinate various fraternity activities through the Interfraternity Council (letter to Dean Bursley from Arthur Lundahl dated June 14, 1939, Vice President for Student Affairs, Box 1, "Fraternities - Resident Advisors, 1933-1949). The position was not continued the next year due to university-wide budget cuts.
A staff position related to Fraternities first appears within the Office of the Dean of Men in the 1951/52 Directory of officers, Faculty, Staff and Associated Organizations. Beginning in the 1951/52 school year, Joseph H. Fee, Assistant to the Dean of Students, held the new position of Fraternity Advisor within the office of the Dean of Men. The duties of this position were transferred to the Assistant Director of Student organizations, Freeman T. Clark in the 1968/68 academic school year. (See list of persons holding the fraternity advisor position).
The Fraternity Office was created by the university to monitor activities and housing policies and to police individual fraternities. The advisor (counselor) to fraternities was also a member of the advisory board for the Interfraternity Office (IFC), a self-governing student organization concerned with maintaining the standards of the fraternity system,.
During the 1960s, the university gradually lessened its control over fraternities. The office was disbanded at the end of the 1968/69 school year. It was decided at that time that fraternities required only an advisor on an as needed basis, which was the current practice for student organizations on campus. (President's Report, 1968/69, Volume IV - Student Organizations, p.2.).
University Officers Overseeing Fraternity Affairs
Fraternity Relations Counselor
1938-1939 Arthur B. Lundahl (graduate student)
Assistant to the Dean
1951-1952 Joseph H. Fee
1952-1956 William S. Zerman
1956-1959 William G. Cross
1959-1962 Louis C. Rice
Assistant to Director of Student Activities and Organizations, Office of Student Affairs
1962-1965 John Feldkamp
Assistant to Director of Student Organizations, Office of Student Affairs
1965-1966 Charles Judge
1967-1969 Freeman T. Clark
The records of the University of Michigan Fraternity Office cover the period 1922-1964. The provenance of the records is unclear. The records appear to have been created in the offices of the Dean of Men, Dean of Women, and the Interfraternity Council, in addition to the Fraternity Office. The records are divided into two series, Topical Files and Greek Organizations.
There are also materials relating to Theta Nu Epsilon, an underground fraternity that generated concern among college administrators across the nation and a 1960 hazing incident involving Theta Xi fraternity. Also of interest are the files on Alpha Kappa Alpha and Delta Sigma Theta, two sororities formed for African American women.
The documentation of this office is in general scant; the bulk of the documentation covers the years 1958-1964.
Subjects:
Greek letter societies.; University of Michigan. Fraternity Office.; University of Michigan. Interfraternity Alumni Assembly.; University of Michigan. Interfraternity Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series consists of five folders. These folders document the activities of the Interfraternity Council (IFC), Interfraternity Alumni Assembly and the Office of the Dean of Men. The IFC folder contains correspondence with the Counselor to Fraternities, statements about the purpose of the IFC, fraternity scholarship reports, and IFC regulations. The Interfraternity Alumni Assembly folder contains the 1926 and 1927 constitution and bylaws of the assembly and scattered minutes.
  - Correspondence 1947-1963 (Box 1)
  - Fraternity Listings 1954-1960 (Box 1)
  - Interfraternity Alumni Assembly of University of Michigan 1926-1963 (Box 1)
  - Interfraternity Alumni Conference 1942-1963 (Box 1)
  - Interfraternity Council 1932-1964 (Box 1)
- Greek Societies
  The Greek Organizations series consists of an alphabetical listing of fraternities and an alphabetical listing of sororities. The files appear to have come from the offices to the Deans of Men and Women, in addition to the Fraternity Office. This series contains histories, member lists, requests by colonies to become active chapters and disciplinary actions imposed by the University of Michigan on chapters.
  - Fraternities
    - Alpha Kappa Lambda 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Phi Alpha 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Sigma Phi 1962 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Tau Omega 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Chi Phi 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Chi Psi 1950-1962 (Box 1)
    - Evans Scholars 1961 (Box 1)
    - Kappa Sigma 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Phi Delta Theta 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - Phi Kappa Sigma 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Phi Sigma Delta 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Pi Lambda Phi 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Psi Omega 1948 (Box 1)
    - Sigma Alpha Epsilon 1962 (Box 1)
    - Sigma Alpha Mu 1961-1963 (Box 1)
    - Sigma Chi 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Sigma Nu 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Tau Epsilon Phi 1956-1962 (Box 1)
    - Theta Chi 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Theta Nu Epsilon 1923-1952 (Box 1)
    - Theta Xi 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - Trigon 1962 (Box 1)
    - Xi Psi Phi 1925-1954 (Box 1)
    - Zeta Beta Tau 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Zeta Psi 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Sororities
    - Alpha Chi Omega 1948-1953 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Delta Pi 1929-1954 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Epsilon Phi 1926-1958 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Gamma Delta 1928-1954 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Kappa 1922 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Kappa Alpha 1933-1964 (Box 1)
    - Alpha Omicron Pi 1947-1960 (Box 1)
    - Delta Sigma Theta 1931-1963 (Box 1)
      (See also Alpha Kappa Alpha)
    - Sigma Kappa 1958-1959 (Box 1)
Related Material
For additional records on the topic of Greek societies at the University of Michigan, the researcher should consult the following record groups, available at the Bentley Historical Library:
University of Michigan. Vice President for Student Affairs.
University of Michigan. Panhellenic Association.
University of Michigan. Housing Division.
The researcher should also consult the Bentley Historical Library's manuscripts and printed works catalogs under the heading of individual Greek organizations for descriptions of manuscript collections and printed materials. Lastly, the researcher should also consult the finding aid for the University of Michigan vertical file.